嗯，誒，各位委員。
就今日呢個誒委員會咧。
關於二零一三信託法律修訂條例草案嘅委員會就。
繼續今日嘅會議。
噉啊，今日咧就係目的係聽取團體同埋個人意見嘅。咁今日有兩個單位，就有團體同埋個人，就會對條誒條例草案咧會作出口頭嘅陳述。
噉啊喺度咧，我哋就開始我哋嘅會。首先咧，就誒先通過上一。
次會議嘅會議紀要。
係就通過幾要誒？之前咧，我哋未收到任何嘅修正嘅建議。
咁喺度，請各位係咪確認咗今次嘅誒上一次嘅會議紀要咧？
好多謝大家，噉我哋就確認咗有關嘅會議紀要。
噉我哋而家就同團體、同政府代表咧就舉行呢個今日嘅會議啦。咁咧就先歡迎呢個當局。
要啊安排嘅人員出席，請佢哋誒入座。
噉啊，同一時間我哋係可以邀請埋佢哋團體咯。
好啊！噉我哋安排埋團體嘅同埋個人嘅，都進入每場。
做嘢，做嘢。
冇理。
啊！早晨，各位官員同埋早晨啊，有關嘅團體。
以後係英文。
Channel number two is for English version.
誒。
啊，今日咧就因為有團體同埋個別人士咧，就係出席呢個。
會議咧，噉我哋就根據佢提交咗嘅有關意見書咧，就。
我哋呢度喺度誒重新就係。
佢哋嘅發言就唔會受到《亞法會權力及特權條例》所定嘅保障同埋豁免嘅。
而陣間咧係團體或者個人咧，都係發言時限咧係五分鐘。
誒團體或個人嘅發言咧，由於會方面，我哋委員會方面已經收到佢哋嘅書面嘅建議書㗎啦，所以佢哋就唔需要重複，唔需要重複。
意見書嘅內容，噉啊喺邀請信裏邊都講明，佢哋集中咧今日會係發言嘅時候咧，就有以下四個方面嘅表達意見。
第一咧係對政府當局回應嘅意見。
第二咧就係廢除反財反財產行計規則裏邊嘅意見。
第三咧係對受託人免責條款作出法定規制嘅管制嘅意見，以及第四咧就係對。
某些情況之下，免除受託人管理同監督相關公司嘅責任嘅意見。
咁咧就以下就我就安排。
順序。
係第一位咧，係Mr。
啊香！
Thank you, honourable members. The Joint Committee on Tax Law Reform wholeheartedly supports the amendment bill.
It is vital to Hong Kong regaining its rightful place as Asia's leading trust administration centre.
The amendments are long overdue. They have been very carefully prepared.
They have been subject to a lengthy and detailed consultation.
process by all of the stakeholders over the last seven or so years.
although we as a committee would have liked the bill to have gone further in certain areas and we have made detailed submissions in in that respect.
We do not wish.
to jeopardise the passage of the bill in its current form in this session.
Mr. Lee and I would be happy to try and answer any questions that the members may have on the bill.
但，with respect to the rule against perpetuities and the rule against excessive accumulations of income.
We would just like to point out.
the following，the rule against perpetuities abolition does not mean that all trusts will be perpetual，it just means that they can be perpetual，set laws can choose a shorter period if they like。
The rule currently is overly complex.
It's out of date.
and unnecessary because its origins are in response to a distinctly Anglican problem, which does not apply in this place.
Our competitors are doing away with it, and we need to do it as well. It is entirely unsuitable for many commercial trusts, such as investment funds and pension funds.
If you'd like to speak about Bart and Barclay, Mr. Lee would be happy to address that issue.
Mr. Chairman, Members, thank you very much indeed. The provision concerning Barclays Bank is a provision that enables those who have companies to be able to allow the directors of those companies to go on running them, despite the fact that the shares are held by trusts.
This is a very important position for many people who hold companies, and that sort of clause is frequently used in the UK to permit that sort of position to happen where there is a trust. I think it's extremely important for ongoing provision.
For trusts and for the industry, that that sort of provision is included. Thank you.
好，噉啊，多謝咗剛才嗰兩位誒有關信託法改革聯合委員會嘅兩位先生。
誒，跟住落嚟嘅咧就係Mr. Johnson。
Yes, good morning, Chairman and Committee. Thanks for the opportunity.
我係個 pension administrator。
and twenty years ago.
Bill O'Hearn and David White, who's colleague of Mark Lee's, sat.
and came up with recommendations on reform of trust law.
係，二十 years。
The paper that was written, I wrote, but any one of us could have written it.
and it contained many recommendations, which are before the bills committee today.
In other words, I think we have an opportunity at last to reform trust law, and I can only urge the bills committee to push this.
作為 pension administrator，我係constantly running up against difficulties in trust law in Hong Kong。
and I wholeheartedly support the abolition of the rule against perpetuities.
when it comes to trying to reorganise pension funds, particularly old pension funds, this can be quite problematic.
The rule is something purely to do with the acceleration of vesting of interests in land, and this really has absolutely nothing to do with Hong Kong.
我亦都説過，就係在有關監管層面，或者説監
standard of behaviour, but you've got to be very, very careful.
When you're defining bad behaviour, especially in trust law, and it's probably better left the courts.
The courts are the regulator in this area, and so if the bills committee is going to go off down the path of even considering some sort of
statutory standard of trustees behaviour, I would recommend only that it be can be kept conceptual and no more than that.
One of the things I think that is not.
誒。
properly understood。
and it's clear from the draughtsman's words in this bill.
是什麼？ exactly is the trustee's standard of behaviour.
你見，你有四個標準。如果你可叫它那樣，你有個刑事標準，係不誠實。
then you've got the law on negligence there, then you've got the reasonable man, and right up the top you've got prudence. That's the trustee standard, and yet we've got in the bill this concept of reasonableness, or a trustee acting on behalf of people. A trustee never does that.
所以，我認為，什麼？法案委員會需要做，如果我可説，是，有個仔細的看，同步這些概念在法案，因為在目前。
The bill has introduced differing standards.
One last remark is to do with.
The Barclays Bank case, which has been sculling around for years.
從某一點觀點，一 has to ask why it is.
That trustees as a special class of shareholder.
holding shares in a special class of company, say a private company, should be treated in some manner or other that's different to all other shareholders.
Well, I can certainly see that trustees do have difficulties, because as a pension administrator, this is something we have to deal with all the time.
I do think that certainly in the area of pension funds.
The liabilities that accrue to pension fund trustees can be quite severe.
所以，當 ten wheels  come off things， as they do。
在股市。
It's always the pension administrators that are to blame. Do you see? And so, from that point of view.
If you go to operate a trust owning shares in in a private business or listed shares, then I think that some consideration needs to be given to limitation of that liability because at the moment it's open-ended.
I think that's all. I could go on. Be pleased to answer any questions if the Bills Committee has any for me.
好，誒多謝以上幾位嘅誒有關嘅提出嘅意見。咁咧就如果有關嘅出席嘅人士咧，就帶咗有關發言稿咧，一間可以喺你嘅稿上邊寫上有關名稱。
然後留畀本會咧，就交畀職員咧，就可以作為本會嘅參考之用。
咁以下咧，我哋就誒請。
誒，當局咧對有關團體同埋個人所發表嘅意見咧，可以作一啲嘅回應。誒，政府方面誒，邊位？
李議長，誒多謝主席，就誒亦都歡迎誒。
今日參加會議嘅。
其他即係工作人士啊，或者業界人士啦，其實。
咁誒，我諗今日都有個主題性嘅討論啦。
噉我但係我諗係誒，其實喺今次嘅討論之前咧，我哋都亦都知悉咗佢哋有關嘅。
誒係關於專題嗰啲問題上邊嘅意見啦，同埋我哋都喺誒之前嘅會議咧，都表達咗我哋有啲嘅睇法。
咁喺誒，首先我都好歡迎咧，就係在座有三位咧都好，好支持依一個嘅條例草案，亦都係誒，我哋都聽到佢哋呼籲誒，依個初審委員會亦都希望支持依個條例草案。咁關於誒，其中有講話誒。
依個誒一個新嘅。
誒誒。
第一嗰個就係話《Properties and Accumulations Ordinance》裏邊，我哋有關嗰個修訂咧。
咁其實誒三位嘅意見咧都同我哋誒嘅建議係一致，當然事實上亦都係我哋係聽咗業界嘅意見咧誒考慮咗之後提出嘅。咁呢個亦都想想睇留翻畀委員會嘅委員咧就誒睇下有冇咩嘅其他誒再有唔同嘅意見，我都明白。
上次有講過，就究竟係一個相對長嘅年期，譬如話八五年。
會好啲定係即係我哋都可以接受到完全冇年期嘅咧？咁噉我哋誒一路咧，我哋都嘗試去誒説服誒議員咧，就係話其實誒我哋考慮過咧冇咗土地嘅問題嘅。咁喺香港嚟講咧，其實我哋都應該可以嘗試一個冇年期嘅一個嘅做法。
法嘅咁噉樣嘅做法咧，就會將香港咧喺依一個嘅喺依個範疇裏邊咧，係帶出香港咧係一個誒，可以話係吸引力咧係相對。
誒任何其他主要嘅普通法嘅國度嚟講咧，係更加好嘅，即係譬如包括英國、新加坡咧，我哋會更加吸引。
咁另外咧就係嗰個所謂Battle vs. Buckley Trust Company Limited嗰個嘅誒情況咧。
我諗誒。
其實嗰個誒，我哋都。
都聽到個意見，但係我哋重新即係依個比較係誒單向嘅意見，因為依一個咧就係一個喺從嗰個嘅受託人嗰個眼光去睇，當然。
我哋都要諗深一層，就係話喺現在嘅情況。
喺普通法嘅制度之下，誒。
就唔同我哋話冇年期嗰個考慮，因為喺普通法嘅其他嘅主要嘅金融城城市嚟講，今日國家誒金融嘅制度嚟講咧，我哋都睇唔到有誒在座三位建議嗰啲嘅修訂。
噉我哋都睇翻咧，就係話誒，依個亦都唔同我哋頭先講嗰個嘅誒perpetuity嗰個問題，因為嗰個都可以揾到咧，裏邊主力土地嗰個考慮，香港冇。
咁喺依一個情況咧，我哋要好好仔細睇，所以我哋喺以前就講咧，就係話我哋喺原則上係有顧慮。
咁誒係咪去到我哋原則性完全係已經可以話不能接受咧？我唔會咁講，但係依一個。
始終裏邊嗰個嘅牽涉，如果佢去到嗰個在underline companies裏邊嗰啲嘅操控啊，嗰啲嘅誒。
會邊一個人如果有有事發生嘅時候需要受誒誒負責人嗰度咧？而家喺普通法之下咧有個處理嘅方式。噉我哋要改變佢嘅時候咧，係需要好仔細去討論咧，究竟係改變到咩程度？喺嗰個主體法例裏邊。
係點樣寫到咧？係可以包含到而家已經咁多種唔同嘅寫法嘅trust deed裏邊咧，都可以咧合適合你哋咧去實施。
噉我哋當然啦，冇辦法可以追翻追尋翻咧，就係話誒一啲嘅誒所謂嘅財產受與人咧，佢哋嘅意向，因為咧其實。
誒喺即係呢個諮詢，即係諮詢嚟講咧，即係其實任何人理論上都可以係一個財產受予人，但係亦都可能佢會覺得自己我都未必會啦，亦都唔會表達意見。所以呢一個咧就變咗係我哋即係喺政府或者喺誒立法會議員嚟講咧，我哋有個前瞻性去要去去考慮。
會唔會喺嗰個佢哋嗰個身份角度，相對於同埋受益人？
嗰個角度。
誒，如果做咗呢一個嘅改動嘅時候咧，對佢哋嘅權益會唔會有一個誒重大嘅改變，而係誒？
係引發嘅後果係。
係想像唔到，或者係控制唔到咧噉，依個所以我哋覺得係誒需要喺一個嘅條例草案以外嘅場合去誒再仔細去研究。咁依個我哋亦都會接受同誒業界誒代表組織咧，就去誒繼續去去聽佢。
哋個意見咧，因為始終我哋都講啦，呢一個嘅條例組，我哋做完咗之後咧，亦都唔係話就此誒算數嘅，因為我哋都係做完咗之後咧，我哋都唔會好似誒以往噉樣要要隔好多年、好多年先至會再重新審視嘅。我哋相信咧，既然即係以今時今日呢個現代社會嚟講咧，金融。
發展咁重要咧，我哋都會咧喺誒條例草案誒落實之後，即係如果係獲通過落實之後咧，亦都唔會太長時間咧係會找尋機會咧係有需要係誒修改或者係更加誒誒改善嘅地方咧，我哋都會去考慮嘅。啊，多謝主席。好誒，多謝政府嘅。
對有關團體同埋個人嘅表達意見嘅回應，噉我相信咧就委員都聽咗即係雙方有關嘅意見，咁咧就我哋一間就會進入一啲較具體嘅誒討論嘅，咁因為我哋按照做法咧就係誒佢哋都有好多書面咧之前嘅都。
誒提供咗畀大家㗎啦，就我睇到有特別嘅新嘅一啲意見，咁所以咧就我哋一間可以參照到佢哋之前留低嘅有關意見，同埋今日政話嘅表態，咁咧就作為我哋今日誒呢個委員會嘅討論。
咁如果冇特別咧，我哋係啊，導演，你哋想問一問啲意見啊。O K，我如果你哋需要問嘅咧，因為通常我哋都畀政府回應咗之後，就如果團體或者個人佢哋有需要咧，就可以離職嘅。但係如果你哋有需要問嘅咧，佢哋如果唔誒唔介意咧，佢哋再留多。
多一陣，咁咧就請委員先發言。
係啊，陶院，你有有意見啊？係誒，主席，我其實咧就係誒誒，都係關心嗰個即係永續誒嗰個誒信託咧，誒尤其是係土地嗰方面嘅。
嗱，即係我上一次咧，即係個會上兩次會，我都提出過咧噉樣。嗱，因為第第一咧，香港咧都係一個啊幾細嘅地方，噉啊有限嘅資源，有限嘅土地。
噉。
我我我睇到個趨勢咧，我我係擔心。當然，你你話推推斷幾廿年後，我唔或者幾百年後，我唔知啊。但係，譬如你而家舉個例咧，係有啲真係內地人咧，係買咗一啲住宅。
而佢好好奇怪喎，佢真係唔住嘅喎。
啊！咁當然佢佢唔住，佢好種種種原因嘅。噉我知道，譬如其中有啲就喺西九龍嗰啲咩咩海傳媒都買個單位噉，擺幾幅名畫，擺擺幾千萬現金喺個保險箱，另外啲古董噉。咁其實佢根本就係當係一個保險箱嚟嘅，根本啊！噉佢又唔唔唔唔唔租。
O.K.噉啊，然後咧就，如果佢真係將來假設真係成成立咗個永續嘅信託。
係永遠咁持續落去，而越嚟越多嘅外邊嘅人唔一定內地人嘅嚇，可能係其他嘅地方都得嘅。咁但係因為我睇到個趨勢咧，就係呢呢呢堆人咧係特別得意咧，就係佢佢真係唔租嘅。OK又唔去誒就處置嘅話噉。
係，如果噉樣。
會唔會即係我哋嘅土地資源咧，就會持續一段時間之後咧，噉就其實係好緊張，好緊張。
咁當然你話哦噉啊，政府可以誒，即係相應有個方法就係誒抽一個咩空置税啊，或者咩噉嘅嘢啦嚇，類似啦噉樣。咁但係我心諗你你你除非你嗰個去到一個好苛刻嘅地步啊，一年咩百分之五十啊噉啊，噉啊冇可能㗎，係嘛？咁咁否則嘅話咧就。
有嗰啲即係誒誒誒財富，財富都唔緊要啊！其他財富都，而係如果特別係土地嘅時候咧，係lock死咗一部分嘅土地，越嚟越累積嘅土地係唔放翻出嚟嘅咧，係只係畀某啲人原來係做保險箱嘅啫，或者某種嘅用途啊紀念都得㗎。
佢OK，或者喜愛都得嘅，收集都得嘅噉。
咁錢就對佢又唔係問題嘅喎。
咁點搞咧咁？嗱，我哋外外地咧，我知道我舉例就譬如話咧。
好多喺誒，就算英國啊，點解好多嗰啲古堡啊嗰啲咁咧？佢自己頂唔順咧，嗰啲家族咧，噉啊好多咧，就種種原因。
但係好多時咧，最後咧就係誒誒嗰個可能係有啲誒費用啊貴過頭啊乜乜咁噉樣佢頂唔順噉。咁但係咧，我自己睇向前睇咧，我真係唔敢講咧個相同嘅出情況咧係可以受制呢樣嘢。
噉，但係變咗咧，就會唔會喺？
我哋都揾揾一個，即係舉個例，誒，就算你而家個限限定咁咁咁咁限制，我哋延長一啲，但係到起碼有一個終結嘅可能性咧，咁變咗咧就我哋冇辦法能夠預測將來幾遠，但係如果我哋而家係定咗呢個規則。
假設啊，你將來突然間你話某個時間，我哋好睏難啊個土地嘅需求或者某樣嘢，然後你轉翻轉頭嘅時候咧，你可能對某啲人工度喎咁噉，係咪其實我哋都唔好去到咁盡係而係定一個時間，雖然係延長一啲，但係定一個時間係比較好啲咧。嗯，好啊。
語言嘅表達，就我想問一問，來來來賓有冇考慮過呢個問題咧？誒，嘉賓有冇呢方面嘅你哋嘅意見咧？
Mr. Chairman, I think the answer to that probably is first of all, the the number of mainland Chinese who presently use trust is pretty small.
What may happen in the future, of course, I cannot tell, and it would be difficult for you sir too as well. I wonder if this solution is best not dealt with not in trust law, but in terms of requiring property not to remain vacant for a period of time.
因此，我建議解決方案不應在這項法案和永續性問題上，而是在其他立法上。
Thank you, Mr. Lee.
啊！
really just to
to reiterate what Mr Lee was saying, I commented on actually Mr Toh on this point.
誒，sorry，我聽我呢度聽越係。
啊，得得，sorry。
因因為冇聲喺度，睇下。Now just just to to reiterate what Mr Lee was saying, I think it's a different legal point that you're raising, and I actually commented on this.
indirectly in a note that I'd sent by email ten days or so ago, the point about perpetuities.
is that it's a rule designed to encourage the vesting of interests in land, so they don't remain unvested. By vested, I mean owned.
and actually in Hong Kong we've already got that. you see nobody owns the land except for the government.
and so you know you've got reversion automatically under any lease. I mean I and my wife own a flat, we we call it our home, we call it we we own it. Well actually all we've got is is the use of it. Do you see? So from that point of view, I don't think that you've got a difficulty under trust.
如果永續性被廢除。
and as Markley was saying, I think it's better dealt with under some other legislation, landlord. We're pretty close to it anyway.
好，誒多謝佢哋，係誒你再要跟進啊！我簡單回應下先。好，個問題咧就即係譬如最，就算最尾個答案咧，我都諗過嘅。
但個問題咧就係你如果中國實行嗰個誒香港一國兩制，咁當然五十年不變，五十年之後你仲可以收翻曬添噉係嘛？但係個問題咧就係如果你一旦實行噉嘅話咧，我覺得將來咧你話要突然間話哦誒個土地誒政府嘅reversion收翻曬全部嘅土地啊！
噉我覺得呢個咧近乎咧係即係不可能啊，非常困難。咁所以變咗咧，即係如果我哋喺嗰個嗱，你話誒之前第一個答案咧就係話，哇係而家內地人咧就唔係咁多用做信堂，但係佢將來佢一旦考慮到呢個係能夠永續嘅時候咧。
咁好簡單咧，佢一好多即係又是中都唔係淨係中國人咧，即係外國人都係嘅啦啊。佢哋嗰個叫個家族啊啊，就世世代代。O K，咁即係世世代代就係某一啲嘢係唔傳落去嘅子孫，然後咧即係唔vest啦。O K，然後咧就。
永續噉樣嚟到去某一種嘅形式。
咁變咗嘅話咧，即係我就覺得誒，如果係去到土地，尤其是香港咁細嘅地方咁有限制嘅咧，噉我就覺得呢個咧就係相當擔心啊。就變咗有香港獨特嘅一啲嘅環境，用同同同處理嘅問題，就唔係直亦都唔係淨係咧誒嗰個信託嗰個即係好空泛嘅概念，而係佢。
去落實到某一個地方嘅時候，噉係唔係會有影響咧？啊，咁當然呢個影響可能近近幾幾廿年、二三十年、三四年未出現嘅，但係將來咧，我覺得我哋可能呢個噉嘅行為咧，就會係影響好大都唔定。你對社會資源嗰個憂慮好啊。噉啊，你大家都表達咗啦。噉啊，我哋。
跟住仲有誒委員問嘅，阿廖長江議員。
Thank you, Chairman. I have a couple of questions. The first questions are for Mr. Henn.
The you say you you say that the competitors are doing away with the rules against perpetuity and the rule against accumulation.
What competitors would that be? I take that to mean that the competitors have abolished.
The RAA and the R and the RAP.
Now, could I, could you tell me what competitors would that be?
And the second question is.
Now, what do you say about having a finite period of perpetuity, like the UK?
That would do away with a lot of the uncertainties and complexities you mentioned about the computation of time. Now, do you do you see that as a possible option for Hong Kong?
未曬香。
I wasn't sure whether you're addressing the question to me, sir. Firstly, in a comparative sense, we have written a table.
which we submitted to the government comparing various aspects of trust law in eighteen eighteen jurisdictions, and I believe that table is before this committee, perhaps.
Yes, but it's it's it's quite difficult. But my colleague Mr. Lee put it together, so I might ask him to tell you which of the other jurisdictions where it is common to administer trusts, this rule has been done away with, so that he can answer your question.
In detail, in terms of the
The other solution, which I think you're suggesting, is to lengthen the statutory period that trusts may exist. That has happened in some places. I know that in the British Virgin Islands, they recently changed their law to extend the maximum period.
that a trust could vest to 360 years.
所以，那那係一個可能嘅解決方案，但係我唔覺得佢去到問題嘅根源，而問題嘅根源係因為條規則本身。
was a response to conditions which honestly do not exist here. So I think making the period longer
Whilst it might be better, doesn't go to the it doesn't cure the the essential fault of the rule and its applicability in modern times and in Hong Kong. Perhaps I'll ask Mr. Lee now to give you a more comparative analysis of the jurisdictions.
interest in the interest of time, maybe I'll take a look at that later. But I have a follow-up question. You said that you see
It has you know basically you're saying that the rule against perpetuities is anachronistic, right? But and of course I heard Mr. Gunson said the the rule is a is about vesting of interest in land. But we all know that trust property, the form of trust property,
Taken a much wider spread, it covers a lot of shows in action nowadays. Now, of course, I can see that the rule against perpetuities can be a bit of a nuisance for trusts and pensions that operate in the financial market.
但， at the same time as legislators, we have to take into consideration.
of trust of a more private nature.
But do you do you see that there should be a distinction?
between a private trust and trust of a more public nature, like those which nowadays operate in the financial markets, and that to have the rule against perpetuities.
confined to the operation of the purely private trusts. What do you say? What do you say to that?
I say that the objections to the rule apply both to trusts for families and those for a wider, a much wider class of beneficiaries. I also think it would be very difficult to somehow define in this.
context，what a private trust was and what a public trust was. I think the other thing we need to remember in the private trust context is that
When we talk about perpetual trusts, it's not as if the beneficiaries don't have a say in these things. Even trusts where the beneficiaries have interests at the discretion of the trustee, if they all get together, they can bring the trust.
到盡，所以有個機制喺現有的法例內，阻止基金繼續進行無限期的時間，如果受益人願意。
我 do see the point of your distinction, but I think it is not one that would be a sensible or easy way to express in the law.
Chairman，just one final question。
Mr. Lee, after some sorry. So, if I just may add, when you're kind enough to look at the comparison chart, yes. Could I just mention that not shown on the comparison chart is what the United States has done, and state by state, a large number of states have now abolished the rule against perpetuities. Right. They've looked at exactly what you've been saying and come.
That conclusion. Yes, thank you. Now, could I
just cite one statement from the Lord Home Commission of the UK.
That.
I believe underpins the philosophy of having a fixed period of 125 years in the UK legislation. May just quote that to you and ask you to respond to that statement.
It says, I quote.
sorry, it's in my cell phone here.
一 significant and very distinguished minority of those who responded.
favour the abolition of the rule against perpetuities.
一 Majority were against this option. However.
他們 consider as the rule still fulfilled the function of controlling the power of one generation to dictate the devolution of property.
That such a function remained an important one.
And that no other rule of law was either sufficient to or as effective in achieving it.
一些respondents consider that the abolition of the rule could have adverse economic consequences.
There was a widespread view that if the rule were abolished.
set laws would undoubtedly create future interest.
which they could not under the present law.
So，what do you say to that？
First, I think it's I'm not sure that I know this is a very difficult problem, but I'm not sure that a comparison with the UK is necessarily the total comparison for Hong Kong.
That's .0.1. .0.2. We've come at this. Sorry, why not?
Because I believe that most trusts and most other things in terms of structuring that are carried out, both for commercial and for other purposes, are better compared with Hong Kong, with say Cayman or Jersey or Guernsey, than it is necessarily with UK.
第二，the trend certainly has been to go towards perpetual trusts in those jurisdictions, and as we've said, it is to a very large extent a voluntary process, and we're looking at assets that have changed vastly from just the landed estates that the UK dealt with at that time, and my.
My colleague has mentioned the question of beneficiaries being able to stop trusts if they choose to at any particular given stage, if they are of full age and capacity to do so.
Yes, but you so you say Hong Kong should follow the example of Cayman Islands and British Virgin Islands. Well, I'm saying that this is the trend and this is what would be necessary, in my view, I'm just my view, but I think held by a lot of other people here, to make Hong Kong competitive in that area and to attract trusts not only.
for private purposes, but certainly for commercial purposes. And the whole of our thrust has been to try and make Hong Kong the base for this industry worldwide, and to look to the ability to benefit Hong Kong from from the changes that are proposed. And I believe this to be one of the
Important factors for that purpose. Well, I'm I'm slightly worried that you say that we should sort of compete with Cayman Islands and British Virgin Islands. Those regimes may not be
I don't think in in the in the in the environment of the future, maybe two decades. You know, it may take a very very different.
You know, things will take very differently with with the.
With the new philosophy now setting in about regulations and all that stuff, global regulations. I think you're definitely right about that. But the consequence of abolishing a rule of perpetuities has no tax consequences whatever. So I don't think that.
如果 we do things that other places do that have zero tax consequences,
I don't think we can be rightly compared to those places for that reason. This is purely a trust law issue, nothing to do with tax.
下位陳建波議員。
誒。
我知道呢個都係好多年嘅努力啦，因為好好耐都冇誒點討過呢個條法例啦。我想問一問咧，問幾位即係今日嚟到最好有機會問一問佢哋咧，就係誒，如果我哋通過呢一紮或者呢呢一呢一呢一係列嘅誒修整咧，其實對香港個競爭力係會增加幾多咧？
相對其他啲信託中心，例如係新加坡，可唔可以講一講個好處係點樣咧？邊位？
哦。
啊，別處理。
Sir， I advised Singapore in 2002。
它 passed its law in 2004.
As the bill now proposed, and we're very supportive of this bill, we would be slightly ahead of Singapore in what Singapore did in terms of changes in two thousand and four.
嗯。
The other.
或 major jurisdiction in Asia was Malaysia, which changed its law in 2010, having started in 2008, and it took a much wider view of the changes that might be made in a number of areas. And here, I simply say that we're very supportive of this bill, and we don't in any way wish to jeopardise its progress, and we wish to.
視它為 law， there are a number of areas such as the Bartlett position and various other things which I believe would be very helpful to make us very competitive. And I can say that in Singapore， the professionals are in some respects and and this is in a paper that we've written， concerned that because they do not
have the methods to use, therefore they are losing business.
好好，下一位阿阿朱議員，我想問嗰樣咁誒嗱，我哋當然唔滿意呢個誒信託法係咁耐先至檢討啦。你覺得係一個咩適當嘅時間咧？即係譬如係兩年啦，定係四年啦、五年咧，去不斷咁檢討同埋係update呢個呢個呢個法例咧，啊，令到你哋係。
係，因為每一兩年都人哋周圍都會不斷去誒改善啊嘛。噉我哋覺得係一個，你覺得係咩釋放時間，令到呢個行業咧係能夠維持有持續性？
Well, so the the we would like to see the law reviewed quite shortly after this amendment bill is made, particularly to look at this Barton Barclay question, and also to reconsider the concept of.
Providing for non-charitable purpose trusts, and you would have seen our submissions in that respect. From a general perspective, I honestly think you don't want the law of trust to be reviewed.
Every two years, it's it's too disruptive to the law. So I would have thought an early review on those specific areas after say two years would be excellent. But I would have thought every five or so years thereafter would be would be more than enough. Is
my opinion.
啊，Yeah, Mr. Ganson.
just to add a couple of remarks, as I mentioned, I'm in the pension business.
And I can tell you that the law as it stands at the moment is preventing us from carrying out.
pension fund work here in Hong Kong. I'll give you two examples.
我安排了轉移 пенси金錢國際上，方案到方案。
And Hong Kong, I'm happy to say, is recognised internationally as a pension scheme jurisdiction. However, if I want to reorganise, say, a U.S. or U.K. pension fund right here in Hong Kong, and I've got one huge example at the moment, I can't.
因為我有個 law on perpetuities 阻我的路， and 我也 got 問題要 do 係有關受託人的負債。
If this bill goes through in its present form, I can guarantee that I get that work, and it's huge and it's expanding. The other example is to do with using Hong Kong as a pension administration centre for Asia.
There's no reason that Hong Kong shouldn't become the premier jurisdiction for pension administration right throughout Asia. It's commonplace for multinational businesses to have Hong Kong as its headquarters. It would be quite logical and efficient for Hong Kong also to be the pension administration centre.
It's great for tax as well. It allows people to move around Asia in their jobs without disruption. So for these reasons, I think you'll find that it is inevitable when this bill goes through that we're going to get a lot of business in Hong Kong.
Mr. Chairman, if I may add one point, generally speaking, this will give us, when I say us, the the trust private trust industry in particular in Hong Kong, the opportunity once we have this as law to go to all of those lawyers and set laws around the world and say.
Come back to Hong Kong, and this is what we've been waiting for for many years, and and and we've got a good story to tell them as to why they should come back if we get this bill in its present form.
阿波，誒，主席，我最後一個問題就係問咧，誒，政府已經就各個有意見嘅人士咧係有個回覆嘅，即係包包括你哋嗰個誒Joint Committee啊，我想問一問你哋仲有冇其他意見？對政府嘅回應有冇其他嘅反應，或者有其他意見咧？
唔知啊？都係噉。
I think so. My view would be that the administration has very kindly listened to.
All our submissions. We've talked very closely with them. We obviously have have.
Thank them very much for the work they've done, and they've done very good work. And we have a bill that we are wholly supportive of.
嗯。
I am concerned, and I think that a number of members of the joint committee are concerned, and the industry is concerned, that it would be very good if we could go somewhat further in the sort of ways that we have mentioned, because our whole emphasis is really the benefit of Hong Kong, and the jobs that will be created in Hong Kong, and the addition to the economy.
of Hong Kong by what we're trying to do, and if, as the administration has been kind enough to say, they are good enough to look further at some of these points, then we shall be that much more competitive, and we will get that much more business—not just of a private nature, but very commercial nature: funds, pension funds, unit trusts, everything will.
Come in that sort of way. I believe that we are the premier centre in Asia, I really do. In terms, I don't speak for me, but I speak for my colleagues because you have the staff and the people and the training and the go in Hong Kong, which frankly Singapore does not have.
At, I think it's time that we really took advantage of that.
多謝啊啊Ken。
Thank you.
聽清未？
繼續。
Thank you, Chairman. The gentleman's argument, both on technical grounds and on business grounds, about the reform of the trust law is—they're well heard.
But as a legislator, as my honourable colleague Martin has mentioned, we have to consider.
the legislation on a wider perspective. Yes, I mean on technical grounds and on business case. Yes, I mean all these proposals are welcomed, especially from the such laws or the trust business perspective.
Now，Hong Kong，is never similar to the UK in terms of its landlord. We never have any freehold land. That is a fact in the past， and that is also a fact， currently.
嗯。
by abolishing the rules against perpetuities, now.
是just a prediction. Of course, we don't we we we we don't have the crystal ball. We cannot see how the economy will be going in what direction in in even five years' time.
Now, by abolishing the rules against perpetuities, there could be a fear that the perception of the settlers and other people would have in Hong Kong is that oh, Hong Kong, yes, we can have a trust that could go.
on on and on forever, and by doing so, because we already have very scarce supply of land, be it just a leasehold.
嗯，how would you predict our land price will go?
If we actually do abolish the rules against perpetuities,
bearing in mind, of course, you gentlemen have a kind of business model that, yes, if
This piece of trust law is passed in the current state, then you have more business, trust business coming to Hong Kong. But would you have a kind of prediction about how our land price would go if we have more trust business? That's my first question. If one of you gentlemen could answer my
my my question first.
I would be very surprised, Mr. Chairman, sir, that.
The abolition of the rule of against perpetuity would have any impact whatever on the land price.
我唔知幾多比例嘅土地。
now in Hong Kong is held through trusts, but I imagine that it's very very small.
一 lot of the land is held by publicly traded companies, so the the interest in land through shares in those companies is a circulating asset. I do not think that the abolition of the rule would create a rush to
嗯。
buy Hong Kong real estate or to put it into perpetual trusts, I think would have.
minimal or or perhaps no impact on that price.
Yes, sure. I quite agree with my colleague. I don't think it would have any impact at all. I also think that the the measures that you have created in terms of stamp duty have had a very considerable impact on people wishing to put Hong Kong property into trusts and other such arrangements.
Well, of course, there's no estate duty in Hong Kong, so there's no incentive for people to do that sort of thing. If it comes to creating trusts, then of course it's a voluntary exercise in terms of how long they have their trusts, and they can be advised appropriately. And frankly, if I just speak for me, I should think that very little.
Hong Kong property is put into trust structures that I have created over the last twenty something years. Certainly, there is land, but that land is not in Hong Kong. And equally, a large amount of the business that I have done not tax driven under any shape or form, but mainly driven
因為
And if I may add one point to address your point, Sir, with respect to perpetual trusts. Speaking personally, I would be very, very careful as an adviser.
Advising a set law to establish a.
Perpetual trust. I think there are places for them, but I think you'd be very, very cautious to allow that possibility. But I think it should be offered under the law.
just very briefly on the point of property prices, I'd like to support what Mark Lee has said. We've actually got nine taxes associated with land in Hong Kong. When you add them all up,
and it's quite striking from the pension administration point of view, to have an entire possible asset class removed.
因為，
and when I was discussing this with can't remember who somebody from the financial services branch a couple of years ago about the impact of of stamp duty, I said that then that
although the government had said that this would hopefully lead to stable property prices, I said no, it won't. It'll increase them.
because it's limiting the supply, it's got nothing to do with perpetuities at all, and I just reiterated would be completely neutral. the the importance of this rule, I think, can't be overstated, and the difficulty that we've got.
is that applies not just to land, it applies to anything that is owned by a legal entity that is assembled in the form of a trust, and I for myself cannot think why one particular form of legal
legal arrangement should somehow or other be singled out.
for a time limit to be placed on it. I mean, why should it? Limited companies can last forever in theory, so can societies. So, from that point of view, I think what we're talking about is is something that is really very different. I would have no fear myself about property prices or the availability of property.
from the。
從的perspective of a pension administrator at all, if this rule were abolished, I think absolutely no effect at all.
I do see that the rule is not, if it is abolished, it's not compulsory for trusts to be perpetual. It's possible for them to be. And beyond that, I think your your worries about property prices and the availability of property are largely driven by.
暫 duty，nothing else。
Well, Mr. Chairman, I have two more follow-up questions.
一，if gentlemen, if you are asked if you want to add one more feature to the current proposed bill, what is on top of your wish list? Is there anything else which is quite important which this current bill has missed?
If you you want one additional feature to this bill, what what what will it be?
We wanted one. I think we we agreed that it would be the Antley, Bartlett and Barclay clause, which allows.
people to put their private companies into trusts.
and。
maintain the management and supervision of them without interference or undue interference from the trustees. That is the thing that I think would really set us apart, and I believe the administration are interested in this idea. And if they
會
主席，可唔可以問行政會答呢個問題？為咩唔可以將佢納入當前法案？因為如果佢哋要喺未來做，就要等另外三至四年。
誒，政府需唔需要做一個簡短嘅回應啊？
誒嗱，首先現在咧喺普通法之下就。
即係喺個trust一個信託嘅制度之下，嗰個財產受讓人咧，佢可以喺唔同嘅方式，佢亦都可以咧係免除嗰個嘅受託人某啲嘅責任嘅。即係如果一個財產受讓人咧，佢係擁有好多公司，好多公司下邊又有附屬公司等等。咁其實咧有好多種型。
食咧。
誒，依個受託人可能會參與一啲公司嘅管理，亦都可能係唔參與。
噉我哋就要睇翻第一，我哋做呢啲嘢，我哋要睇三方面財產受益人。
受託人同埋受益人。
咁實在，我哋頭先一路聽落去嗰個嘅説法咧，就係話。
誒受託人嗰個角度就話：，誒我如果係噉嘅情況之下，我有情況可能我唔會參與嗰個運作嘅。咁如果有事嘅時候，咪我又會咩咯噉樣。咁呢啲嘢其實喺嗰個成立一個個信託嘅時候咧，本來應該個受財產受益人同個受託人咧已經傾妥佢哋之間嘅。
責任同埋佢參與嘅程度，咁所以我就話其實喺現在嘅階段咧係有情況，其實佢可能係已經透過大家商討做嗰個財產誒受託嘅時誒嗰個信託嘅時候咧已經處理咗一樣嘢，但係最主要就係話呢個業界所提出呢一個嘅誒誒建議咧就。
話喺嗰個法律上上邊咧，好明確去寫明咧，基本上差唔多喺任何情況之下咧，佢都係免除嗰種責任。即係如果我冇認，我冇瞭解錯。
噉嘅時候咧，我就要睇翻就係話依樣嘢噉，即係個噉啊，cross the board嘅一個做法咧。
誒。
就噉樣喺第三者聽，就好似啊，完全保障曬受託人啦。
咁當然，即係依啲冇話即係淨係誒向一邊嘅，因為當然喺嗰個商討嗰個價錢方面就會考慮埋嘅。咁但係我就要諗下。
我哋聽到受託人嗰個嘅説法啦，但係我哋都要好了解翻，即係依一啲嘅運作。而家點解依啲誒個情況會佢覺得有問題咧？受託人如果覺得佢而家已經可以誒嗰個誒財產所有人覺得而家喺信託佢寫法嘅時候，其實已經大家可以針。
著個字眼寫啦。
咁如果第日無論點寫都好啦，其實佢都去免責嘅，咁即係我唔需要去負責嗰啲嘅嘅情況嘅時候咧，嗰個我哋都要瞭解下，即係其實喺。
財產受益人同埋受益人嗰個角度，佢哋會唔會又覺得係有啲咩嘅誒問題咧？
咁所以，我哋就係話要掌握多啲先至可以去去確定到，同埋當然最終再要去到去寫嗰個條文嘅時候咧，要好清楚，因為我哋係冇得睇任何而家一啲主要嘅普通法國家任何一啲嘅參考嘅，係冇嘅。O K O K嗯，好好多謝Mr. Chairman，One one more question if I may。嗯，I un
我理解從Mr. Gunsen的提交，那係一段包含，許可投資的清單，要由受託人投資。而Mr. Gunsen建議一種謹慎的態度，係正確的嗎，Mr. Gunsen？而不是給出許可投資的清單給受託人。
So something that I've been banging on about for about 20 years. It's it's if you're looking at benchmarks. I'm sorry, Chairman. I won't take a lot of time. It's it's my favourite subject.
If you're looking at benchmarks internationally on trust law, the prudent man rule is clearly the international benchmark. The difficulty with a legal list of permitted investments.
是， that it is inherently not prudent just to rely on that list. Just because you invest on the list doesn't make it prudent to do so. That's the difficulty with having a legal list. It's all very well to say, well, you know.
it makes it makes it easy for Auntie Chen and Uncle Albert and Monkock and they're administering the deceased estate, but I'm afraid it doesn't work out like that. And the the real test of of any rule on trustee investment is whether or not beneficiaries are better off, and it's very clear from the studies that have been conducted.
Over many years internationally, that prudent man rule is by far the best, and I would believe that that's the direction in which Hong Kong should go. If it doesn't do that, it's going to become an aberration as the default position. We can we can write rules all day long as as to how we want to invest, but
But prudent man rules the default position, and certainly that's the case for pension funds.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Can I ask the administration to answer this particular point? Because I understand that under the current proposal, there are certain classes of, of course, in the old trust laws, where there are classes, there are certain classes of investment which are prohibited, and beyond.
That it will be up to the agreement between the sett law, between the trustee and the sett law, into which you know categories of investment the trustee can make. So, so is the prudent man approach relevant here, or have you not tried to you know incorporate those?
You know principles. Thank you.
係啊，誒主席，如果係講緊係誒喺個信託裏邊可以投資啲乜嘢咧，其實。
誒，首先我哋。
再重新翻咧嗰個嘅schedule咧，其實係如果嗰個嘅信託文書裏邊咧係冇講明，即係冇講到係可以投資啲乜嘢嘅時候咧，就係一個default嘅position啊嘛。即係我想我哋就話咧喺做生意喺做一啲嘅誒，譬如話吸引一啲係真係好好誒有經驗嘅。
嘅誒誒投資者，即係變咗信受誒呢個財產受益人。
誒或者係一啲喺商業運作上咧，其實我我哋見到現在其實好多已經係唔會用嗰個嘅schedule嘅，佢自己已經喺嗰個信貸民資做咗佢哋要投資啲咩高風險嘅嘢，投資乜嘢咧，咁已經做咗啦。依個唔係我唔係講緊schedule of care，我哋講緊係投資嘅範範數嘅啫。
噉我哋喺誒介紹呢個嘅誒條例草案時，亦都講翻呢一個我哋保留誒呢一個嘅誒附件，誒再加翻誒再加埋一個嘅誒經過上次金融風暴之後，即係金融海嘯之後，我哋見到誒一個一個項目咧，我哋係講緊咧，因為真係睇到呢個信託。
裏邊實在係頭先講啦，即係好多家庭式啊，或者私人式啊，一啲係唔係咁專業嘅誒誒信託誒嗰啲財產受益人。噉我哋即係話佢亦都有可能咧，係相對於可能好專業嘅誒誒受託人，但係佢哋未必會揾啲好專業嘅受託人做㗎嘛。佢哋可能真係揾朋友之間。
咁嗰啲咧就真係可能會用到嘅，咁所以我哋就話基於嗰個原因咧，依個唔係強迫性用嗰個schedule嘅附件嘅，個附件係可以幫到依啲人嘅情況嘅。係，好多謝。噉啊，依一節嘅時間已經足夠。啊啊，主席唔好意思。係。誒誒，因為誒關於三位誒誒參與者咧，我。
有關頭先阿陶議員有個問題咧，誒其頭先阿阿阿強咧就有有回覆嘅噉，但係因為陶議員離開咗咧，我都有個補充嘅誒問題咧，想澄清，等佢澄清澄清嘅啫。因為陶議員講咧就話嗰個嘅誒永續嘅問題咧，當然我哋講緊香港嚟講土地就唔係嗰個問。
問題，但係陶議員咧就講緊土地上邊興建嗰啲樓，嗰啲嘅誒誒。
嘅單位，如果係有人誒擁有咗之後咧，就用咗依一個嘅情況咧，就係永續地。
唔唔係用嚟係真係用一個嘅誒有效地運作啦，所以咁講啊，即係畀人住啊咁等等。咁但係誒頭先就誒誒誒Mr.強咧，就係除咗話依個同土地嘅分開嚇，因為始終將來如果政府譬如九九九年期啦，如果到咗之後咧，當到時嘅。
政府亦都可以睇翻。雖然阿陶議員以前有講過咧，就係話你唔通你真係全部收翻曬咩噉樣？但其實咧都可以睇個情況咧，就係話誒，佢到時用咩條件先至可以再續咧？咁到時可以諗㗎嘛，即係呢啲可以好全方位去諗，即係究竟喺價錢上啊，定係使用上，到時嘅政府可以去諗。
點先可以續呢個嘅地地租㗎嘛？除此之外咧，就係話誒呢個單位嚟講咧。頭先阿阿Mr.強咧有提到，就係佢唔係講單位，而佢講一般性咧，就係話我就算永續嘅一個信託咧，誒其實都有有啲情況有可能係，譬如話有啲受託人同呢個嘅。
誒呢個受益人喺最終有啲情況，其實都可以將佢誒停止咗嘅。
噉我就想啊，Mr. Chan咧就係誒，如果相對於陶議員講嗰種情況。
即係一個。
一個人，如果佢真係買咗單位，我用一一個單位嚟講咧，一個人買咗個單位，如果佢做將佢做咗一個永續信託，咁理論上就係嗰個人就係將嗰個誒單位咧，就係永續地去做某啲嘅嘢嘅啫，就唔係畀人誒就諗住一路永遠都係噉樣用㗎啦。噉嘅情況係有。
有冇頭先啊誒所講有冇嗰啲情況可以最終有可能又會停咗佢嘅咧？啊，即係依一個我諗即係誒誒，Mr. Henry可唔可以係澄清佢頭先嘅講法係講一般性定係可以套用翻喺頭先阿陶議員所講嗰個嘅誒佢？
個疑慮嗰方面咧，噉。
冇事啊！
I, Mr. Chairman, I think you're speaking about the rule in Saunders and Vautier.
誒，perhaps啊，主席或者我好簡短講講英文啫，就係。嗯，the point is you you you've mentioned that even in in trust under without a limited period。
There are circumstances under which the trustee with with the beneficiaries may may put it to the end to an end.
Trustees just the beneficiaries on their own. So if the beneficiaries are all of age and capacity, get together.
They can bring any trust.
到一 end at any time， regardless of how long the trust instrument says the trust may go on for， or even if it is perpetual。所以，它 not as if the beneficiaries are powerless to end these trusts if they want to。 and I think that's a very important point。主席，噉就係話關於台語員嗰個。
係，if if we are focusing on on a trust under which the the settlor just put his property into perpetuity。
and。
does does that still apply? Does what you said in unusual circumstances is that the specific beneficiary under that trust? No, it's it's an old case called Saunders and Vautier, but the idea is that if all the beneficiaries who we know, all the ascertainable beneficiaries, who are of legal age, so the
都係成日講話，係咪？
have capacity, they can together get together and say to the trustee, we don't want this trust anymore.
transfer the。
property to us directly, and and the trustee must.
嗯。
adhere with that direction.
係誒，你想跟進呢條腰啊？主席，我想即係comment on this particular question only. Okay. Because I think this is not well.
The general position is yes. I mean, if the beneficiaries of full age and legal capacity get together, they they can end the trust and ask the trustee to transfer property to unanimous agreement by the beneficiaries. But there are quite a lot of exceptions to this rule. For example, I can think of is for example.
If the beneficiary is only entitled to the income of a property and not, you know, periodically, I don't think that that it is quite difficult for them to get together or to to to form a view. Or for example, there may be cases under which the beneficiary is just a group of people.
你Cannot even identify who who are they? Then it will be quite difficult. So I think we we need to get the legal position right. Whether this is you know the termination of a trust by the unanimous agreement of the beneficiary is the the general case or not? I think perhaps, Chairman.
Could I ask our legal advisers to to give us some written opinion on that? Thank you.
嗯。
包括咪可以提供，好OK，誒佢之後可以提供嘅。誒石議員，你係咪？多謝主席。主席啊，我想誒問一問啊啊叫一叫啊Mister David Gan臣咧解解釋佢嗰個，因為我我睇到幾有興趣。
Mr. Ganson, on your submission paper one hundred and eight, on the on your D aspect on the prudent man approach, prudent man law, how do you relate that to to E of your same submissions? Does this give a sense of?
conflicts in there. Can you just elaborate between?
D and E of your submission paper, 1089.
your your your submission to the chairman of bills committee.
on your on your point D and related to point E.
你有那paper？
which is an interesting concept， you know。
You're you're referring to in E the idea of regulating trustees? Yes, on the prudemen rule. The two separate things, Mr. Sheikh. Yeah, I want to know how that's separate, and then somehow it's related into the whole concept. You know, well, if you can elaborate a little bit more, I'll give you the time to do it. When, as I mentioned.
mentioned before, I'm not sure if you were here. The question of prudent man rule is purely to do with trusty investment law itself. In other words, the scope
Of a trustee's investing powers, because a trustee can only do what it's empowered to do.
And so that's that. That purely to do with trustee investment law. What I'm referring to in E is a general comment that it it comes around from time to time, not only in Hong Kong but in other jurisdictions on whether or not trustees themselves
should be regulated. This is nothing to do with trustee investment law, but the regulation of trustees. Now, in certain areas, there is regulation of trustees. For example, in the pension arena, there is regulation of who can be a trustee and the standards that they have to meet. There's no.
conflict between these two points, one being to do with trustee investment law generally, and the other one a question conceptually of should we be regulating all trustees? And my view, for what it's worth, and I think it's a very commonly held view, is that the regulation of all trustees.
作為，
Is not such a good thing to do. I mean, we've got regulators already. They're called the courts, and they've been very successful over the years regulating trustees. So, I hope that's explained what I had in mind, Mr. Sheikh, in those two paragraphs. But can you elaborate on the the the e the e
Paragraph to the extent that I mean, talking about your the papers of 20 years and which is quite interesting to the extent that concept, just like you to elaborate on that aspect of how this would affect the the present legislation.
你你mean regulation of trustees？
I think that what you will find what would happen is that you would have first of all a regulator who was effectively competing for jurisdiction with the court. I mean, we've seen this in other areas. Do you see whether it's to do with the Securities and Futures Commission or other similar regulators?
There is a question of who is the primary regulator and.
它 raises the question of why do you need to have a regulator of trustees at all? I mean, take for example, a deceased estate.
And it might be big. It might be.
Big at all? Who who knows?
The point there is that you immediately run into the difficulty. If you're going to have a law saying that we're going to regulate trustees, you're going to run into all sorts of difficulties. Do you see? If people simply don't qualify.
As trustees, and yet they they are named in a will.
And similarly, where you want to reorganise, say pension funds, I mean I've got this at the moment, they are already regulated. So all you're going to do is impose another layer of regulation on top, and I can't really see to what good purpose. I mean just because a person
嗯。
is a is a is a public company. It's a trustee, whether it's owned by a bank, doesn't make any difference. I think at all. So to me, the the whole idea of trying to create a regulatory body for trustees is going to just
The slow, expensive, and it ain't going to work.
Thank you.
唔好。
誒多謝今日出席嘅有關嘅嘉賓，就我相信都好有益嘅一個大家交流，就亦都瞭解咗好多誒特別業界佢哋嘅睇法，政府方面咧亦都有啲誒。
有相關嘅回應噉啊！呢個財顧問方面有啲再稍後再補充喺書面。噉我諗我哋今日先多謝咗嚟出席嘅幾位嘅嘉賓啊！我代表委員會啊，再一次多謝你哋啊！噉我哋下邊嘅時間咧，就將會委員會再重複啊。
討論翻今日其他嘅內容。And thank you, Mr. Chairman and members, for giving us the opportunity to speak. Thank you.
多謝。
Thank you very much.
誒，我哋就下邊嘅時間咧，就將會係討論翻有關嘅條文嘅。噉我哋先讓呢個嘉賓先離席咗先。
咁咧就。
因為今日嘅時間咧，本來就有如果有充裕咧，我哋可以誒可以再進行一啲逐項，即係或者逐條嘅逐項條文嘅一啲討論嘅。咁咧就時間咧仲有大概十五分鐘。誒，我想問問政府方面，你哋想？
想開始咗呢啲條文嘅討論先。
好啊，主席，我哋可以爭取分。稍等等，阿梁繼聰議員。主席啊，可唔可以問一問各位委員，仲有冇一啲原則性嘅問題想講？咁剩翻，即係如果有嘅話，即係剩餘嘅時間可以講埋佢。如果唔係，即係一開始咗我就覺得會有一啲嘢，我令我我我我哋可能係冇時間去考慮移樽。
入咗咁太過仔細嘅條文嘅時候，會會有啲反效果啦。唔該，主席。都唔緊要，好。咁誒，我喺度再啊花少啲時間咧，去聽聽啲係多謝。
誒有關原則性嘅問題，就睇下委員裏邊咧，對於整個即係頭先實際上都特別業界方面咧嘅反應咧，就都好好正面嘅，即係好支持而家儘快要修訂嘅。不過當當中咧就睇嚟係誒，我嘅感覺就係話有啲咧就係。
完善嘅過程裏邊嘅，可能唔會即刻一次過完善得曬嘅。噉啊，就噉，所以我希望聽聽底下阿梁家俊嘅提法，就係原則性嘅問題，大家剛才聽咗啦。誒，係未進入條文嘅逐項審議之前，仲有啲咩需要大家可以討論一下嘅？
誒，如果可以嘅，就變咗到逐項條文嘅時候咧，就啲細節嚟㗎啦。噉就係嗰度就可以誒，你話減減功夫又得，咩都得，都係係嗰啲叫細即係細嘅項目嘅跟進，即係技術性嘅跟進啫。咁而家我先聽聽睇有冇委員。
對於剛才聽咗嘅同埋之前嘅誒對上嘅會議有關原則性嘅，今次成個進項文件相差咗幾十年之後呢個修訂，同埋亦都可以講話變化咗，又有啲擔心就係話土地資源嘅緊緊缺啊。頭先提一啲問題，但係回應。
嘅方面咧，好清楚，就佢哋覺得喺信託方面咧，對於呢啲即係土地性嘅啊，或者啲實物性嘅誒，我哋依依類嘅資產咧啊，即係所謂固定資產嘅土地資產咧，就似乎唔係。
喺佢哋嘅印象中，唔係太多嘅喺信託影響嘅。
啊，咁呢點咧？我相信亦都誒可能會喺度變化當中嘅嚇，即係誒日後會唔會喺呢一方面遇到嘅咧？噉就嗰個就會係我睇法就係會係頭先講嘅一段時間就要要reveal嘅，即係要重檢嘅。而家時候有幾多咧？
就稍後咧，我覺得都不妨可以做啲做一啲調查，即係特別係政府即係行政當局喺信託嘅範圍內。
有幾多係固定資產，特別係所謂啲誒相當耐嘅歷史嘅一啲誒房屋啊，或者之類嘅啲固定資產已經係lock咗啊，鎖咗喺度，係冇喐到咧。咁甚至係空置咧啊！如果用緊嘅冇問題咧，始終啲人要用。
係嘛係大量嘅空置而係用咗信託咧，咁呢個係唔係有辦法做一啲研究或者調查咧？咁呢一點咧，不妨可以諗諗嘅。係啊，主席，其實如果係你，既然而家提出咗呢個問題咧，其實可唔可以誒業界甚至政府而家畀到些少嘅數據或者資？
知了，我哋究竟喺一個信託入邊有幾多係係鎖鎖緊咗呢啲固定資產？因為其實即係我頭先都提出咗啦，即係話信託其實呢一條嘅信託修訂條例咧，其實對個業界係有好處，對我哋嘅經濟亦都係好處。但係你更加個大層面，唯一一個考慮就係話會唔會因？
而咧，而令到我哋嘅土地嘅資源更加短缺，而即係推高咗我哋嗰個啊地價，甚至樓宇嘅價格。呢個係我諗大家即係朋友都關心嘅問題。如果我哋有啲資料嘅時候咧，我哋會更加會又可以一個掌握係點樣去令到呢一條條例誒點樣去通過，點樣去審。
而咧會有多啲嘅嘅嘅資料啦嚇，唔該主席。好啊，咁政府方面可唔可以睇下針對呢個所謂誒關注或者一啲擔心，做少即係做多一啲啊，唔係做少啲啊，做多啲咁多嘅功夫，去令到誒有啲資料啊能夠拎到出。
嚟嚟到睇，大家喺呢一點嘅預計方面咧，係嗰個即係社會嘅擔心會少啲咧。噉，誒，主席，我諗係頭先喺誒業界嗰個嘅代表咧，都講咗，即係佢喺佢個處理方處理接觸到嗰啲呢個情況，講出嚟，其實。
喺誒政府角度咧，因為喺規管上咧，喺誒。
信託裏邊佢係擁有啲乜嘢嘅物業，佢係用用啲咩物，即係有啲咩嘅物業，有啲咩嘅資產咧，係唔需要登記嘅，所以係我哋唔會有依個嘅資料嘅。咁所以咧，其實咧就係即係根究底都會去翻真係業界佢去做個信託誒受託人嘅時候咧，佢個處理嗰啲啲咩嘅資產咧噉樣個。
嗰度去出發嘅，咁所以頭先咧，其實誒，所以唔會係有一個嘅誒誒數字上嘅資料，而係嗰個嘅概略性。你頭先我相信個業界嘅代表咧都講咗㗎啦。
咁即係，但係咁亦都係即係。
即係無論點咧，就算佢頭先講咗嗰個情況咧，相信即係議員都係即係講緊。
將來會係點？即係如果改變咗改變咗呢個遊戲規則啦，改變咗係泳逐啦，咁又會唔會啲人嗰個嘅嘅behaviour，佢個處理方式又唔同咗咧？咁呢個都係真係一個誒judgement咯，就主席。
咁嗱，我就建議咧，就可以透過一個即係佢好似上一次一個相當詳細嘅意見書嚟自一個學會嘅。我唔知記得係咪信託誒咩係學會性質嘅。
咁如果我哋能夠接觸一下，即係話包括秘書處，我哋都可以幫幫手啊。接觸一下咧，喺學會嘅角度咧，可唔可以提供一啲佢哋嘅一啲資料咧？啊，或者佢有研究咧，或者佢可以透過一啲資訊性嘅收集行行業嘅情況咧，咁嚟到睇一。
到所謂呢啲噉嘅類似嘅房產性質嘅信託裏邊嘅資產嘅佔嘅比例係有冇一個？
即係普藥物嘅數咧，肯定唔會係一個準確嘅數。噉樣都係都係我哋喺今次一個咁大嘅修，即係咁長時間之後嘅修訂嘅時候嘅嗰個關注，可以做嗰啲功夫啊。噉我諗呢個都係，如果委員係同意啊，我諗必須記低呢樣嘢咧。我哋同有關嗰個機構。
聯絡一下，作為委員會嘅要求啊！
嗯，係誒，主席，我我同意你做法。其實我都唔係話想點樣去去去預計將來個市場反應點樣，因為以呢個預計其實都都冇辦法做到。我其實想攞嘅一啲誒比較概括性嘅資料，都係而家現有嘅狀況係幾多，即係做到就做咯。希望都有多少少資料啊，亦都印證到誒咩生。
啊，係夠頭先所講嗰部分咧，即係佢佢覺得係好少嘅啫。咁咁噉，我哋都可能到時學會誒向呢啲業界誒攞一啲誒誒冇冇鑑證嘅一啲資料嘅提供。噉嘅時候，最後收集到之後，可能比例百分之二十、百分之十五之類嘅數據咧，我。
我哋都係做好適當嘅瞭解嘅功夫，係咪啊？
係啊，Martin，你有意見？係啊，主席啊，我當然仲話聽到好多即係業界嘅意見啦。但係我而家聽到係業界嘅意見，係啲professional嘅嘅意見，啲專業人士嘅意見啦。其實呢個信託咧就唔淨係只單，唔係淨係概括，只係業界裏邊嘅利益嘅。
咁所以咧，我就因為其他啲咧就係好難會有一個聽到佢哋其他啲即係比較上私底下嗰啲嗰啲做信託嗰啲嘅嗰啲聲音，因為佢哋係唔同即係冇一個行業㗎嘛。咁變咗咧，就係我有少擔心咧，就係我哋聽啲嘢未必係一定係好全面嘅。嗱，我我更正你，依個又有一個行。
業嘅，即係我自己係信託公司嘅董事長，噉啊行業咧就有，但係就誒可以講話互相之間咧就唔會太多嘅流通嘅，因為佢好多客客户嘅資料係的確係好保密性嘅，咁所以同埋啲資產咧，你知即係敏感性，咁所以就會可能。
係唔會互相通得到好多資料。頭頭先我所講咧，學會咧都係仲係一種研究式咧，可能會攞到些少資料都唔出奇，但係咧都都唔容易，即係包括政府都唔容易攞到誒好準確嘅所謂資產嘅具體分配嘅數據嘅。主席，我唔係講緊誒嗰。
類譬如話，我本人我都可以set up個trust嘅，我可以叫我姨媽、叫我姑姐嚟做trustee，即係呢啲噉嘅嘢咧，係冇一個行業有代表性㗎嘛。嚇，OK，啊石禮議員，你有意見？誒，對唔住，我想叫政府畀畀個文件答覆呢個大律師公會嗰篇。
誒誒，畀我哋嗰篇誒誒誒資料咧，就噉係嗰啲好去帶出好幾個問題喺度咧。即係今日大律師公會今日冇人嚟啊，因為提供足夠嘅資料啦。係啦，噉佢哋點回答誒大律師公會嗰度咧？喺我哋嗰條條例嗰度係佢哋會做㗎。
一定唔會做啊！咁可唔可以有個詳細啲解釋喺度，主席？係啊，政府方面對呢個係誒。
多謝議員啦。就誒，大大師公會裏邊咧有講嗰啲部分問題咧，其實係我哋以前係討論過，或者係我哋考慮過。噉你話佢。
佢寫咗之後咧，我哋有咩嘅回應咧？誒，我可唔可以？
我唔係而家畀，我叫你書面書面畀張誒誒畀張。即係佢佢哋嘅，你哋對佢哋嘅回應嘅一個副本畀我哋。因為我係想，即係有時一依條一忽個忽啊，主席，就我想睇翻一一有政府一篇文件點去回應大律師公會喺依誒佢哋嗰啲誒嗰個張誒。
畀我哋嗰個建議啊，各各方面嗰啲喺喺度，咁咧有一一一整又係成套喺度咧，噉我哋容易睇啊，主席。我哋即係唔係需要你而家即係百倍答覆，唔係唔需要而家答啊，你而家答都冇需要你哋嘅回應嘅回覆，啊，你哋對翻大律師公會嘅有關回應，好嘛？嗯，好，阿何何張議員。
誒誒，主席，就係關於大師公稿裏邊咧，就提誒嗰個意見書裏邊咧提到嗰啲豁免條款啊嚇，即係嗰度誒，關於個gross negligence即係個係咪叫嚴重疏忽啊？我唔知道點譯啦嚇，佢希望有個有個定義啦噉樣，噉我就當然就一方唔睇政府點點回應啦，但係第二方面咧，我我想。
誒誒，政府或者法律顧問都好咧，都可以畀啲資料我哋咧。其實一對呢啲噉嘅豁免條款咧，仲有第二啲條例係有啲管制嘅。
啊！即係譬如咩啊，control exemption clauses ordinance，好似有一個噉嘅條例，我唔。
誒或者unfair contract act都可能會有影響到呢啲噉嘅。
啊！un unfair contract ordinance嗰啲乜嘢，可唔可以誒？可唔可以畀誒一張文件講講咧？究竟有咩嘢嘅條例係影響到呢啲豁免條款嘅有效性？咁而依家呢度嗰個修訂或者不修訂？
誒同呢啲噉嘅條例誒之間嘅關係點樣，會唔會影響到嗰啲條例嘅運作？大家知道呢呢個係好緊要嘅，呢個呢個噉嘅誒，即係對嗰啲豁免條款嚟講咧，我我係非常之關注，即係佢嘅有效性啊，或者係。
係，阿姚生，你回應。
誒誒。
啊啊！
主席，誒，因為其實之前咧，可能都有嘅簡短討論過呢個問題。因為其實咧，誒頭先啊，何議員提過一啲嘅法例咧，其實佢咧就誒可能只係適用於合約，而一個trust deed咧，因為佢本身唔係一個合約嘅形式咧。誒，根據我哋嘅理解同埋法律意見咧，似乎咧嗰啲嘅管制咧係唔適用於trust deed嘅情況。
咁而家我哋嘅理解，根據誒trusted嚟講，個exception cost嗰個誒control咧，只係誒源於嗰個誒普通法入邊嗰個管制，就係咧就係唔容許咧係誒，即使有呢個誒fraud嗰個情況咧，都可以exception啦，譬如暫時嘅情況就係噉。咁至於關於嗰啲contract嗰啲，就唔適用於誒信。
學文書呢一方面嘅。
O.K.誒，但係即係我想跟跟進咧。
其實嗰啲本身啲可能啲有啲contract嘅，即係有啲合約嘅性質喺裏邊㗎嘛。譬如你你個你個啲裏邊會有提到誒，即係誒大家之間嘅關係。譬如你聘用嘅條件啊，聘用誒包括到你畀咩嘢薪酬佢。跟住咧，你亦都會講到話佢咩情況真係需要。
負上責任或者唔負上責任，噉你知道大家要簽字。
即係譬如佢佢舉例嚟講，嗰個嗰個誒誒誒誒去到創辦呢個信託嘅人，都要簽落嗰張啲度嚇，簽落嗰張嗰張嗰張嗰張嗰張契約度咧，你先至會有噉嘅，先至會受到約束㗎嘛。所以誒，政府政誒即係即係政華所講嘅意見話，喂啲。
將個跌，所以就冇唔係合約，我就覺得有啲關心咯。如果係噉嘅話咧，
對唔住啦，噉我就可能會引將嗰啲依家嗰啲條例裏邊嘅管制咧，我就想加入呢個呢個呢個信託信託人嗰個條例嗰度啦。我就唔會滿足於咧，淨係取即係淨係加上嗰個誒闊面嘅close close negligence，即係唔誒淨係適用於close negligence，我覺得唔夠啦。我就好加埋嗰啲不合情理啊！
嗰啲嘢落去啦。如果倘若即係你個觀點係噉樣，我我唔知我哋法律顧問會唔會有諗法，或者今日誒你需要翻去諗諗。好，遲啲嚇畀啲意見我哋嚇。啊，法律顧問可以記低，畀翻一啲誒法意見。
係就誒，因為時間都差唔多㗎啦，所以咧就嚟趕趕快少少提埋你哋嘅意見咧，畀下一次之前就做啲準備。係啊，阿Martin先，再到阿Ken。
主席啊，我完全同意係係合約咧係唔適用。點解我話合約係唔適用咧？大家開作為一個參考資料，因為合約嚟講，你係兩個人去，大家去一個係公平嘅一個情況之下咧，係達成一個合約條款，所以佢免責條款咧都有。
有免責條款，但係又比較上低層次啲。但係如果你係一個信託嘅環境之下咧，係有一個我哋叫做fiduciary relationship，一個係絕對信任嘅一個一個一個關係嚟嘅。咁呢個免責條款嚟講咧，即係個嗰個嗰個信託人，即係管理信託嘅嗰個人咧，係嗰個。
責任啊，係比一個普通一個立約者咧係更加為高嘅，所以變咗咧就佢個免責條款嗰度咧係要畀，應該係要畀呢個contract嗰度咧係更加，即係一個普通嘅合約嘅嘅情況咧係更加要高一層。
啊！阿Ken，你係係主席啊。其實我都想即係法律顧問或者係政府畀翻多少少關於呢一個合約同埋一個deed，究竟即係control exemption clause啊等等係咪會apply呢樣嘢？嗱，其實阿阿阿Martin都提過係啦，即係喺個trust立別嚟講咧，嗰個信託。
人嗰個duty一個快duty duty應該係高啲嘅噉，但係係咪所有即係關於合約嘅所有嘅條例都唔用到喺嗰個信託入邊咧？我又直覺上覺得未必係呢件事，因為其實一個跌一個契約其實都係一個好特別嘅合約。
即係呢個係我諗，大家讀過喺大學讀過法律都知嘅係一個好特別嘅合約。就點解就你就唔apply咧？喺喺喺呢個情況底下，即係我都想誒誒法律顧問，甚至誒誒誒administration可以畀翻一張詳細少少嘅嘅嘅文件，可誒針對呢一個誒重點去講一講，好冇？
啊，多謝主席。嗱，噉啊，我相信法律顧問同埋誒政府方面都聽咗。噉我哋分別都希望能夠畀到一個誒針對性嘅意見。誒喺書面方面咧，喺呢個會之後咧，提供畀我哋。
可以嘛？
因為太多懸念啦，好似，因為我哋由頭到尾都係講緊咧，所有喺trust裏邊講嗰啲exception咧，就話所有嘅case我哋睇翻曬喺普通法，即係所有case都因為fraud先至可以免責，即係即係先唔可以免責噉，所以就話即係我哋有，即係我哋源於一個，咁所以即係係有分別，咁但係我哋會睇翻。
冇錯。
好，噉啊嗱，今日。
即係頭先聽唔到政府，佢會畀翻張誒民建，我哋關於大律師公會嘅，係啊係嗰個嗰個會即係大律大律師公會嚟嘅意見嘅一個回應嘅一個書面，我哋都應該會收到一份。好啊，唔該。噉啊嚇噉啊嗱誒，其他事項啦，因為時間都夠啦，咁咧就提醒大家。
咧就下一次嘅會議日期咧就會定喺六月四號星期二嘅下午四點三十分至六點三十分。如果之前咧我哋希望能夠收到有關文件之後咧，我哋一開始嘅時候咧，如果係冇特別意見咧，可以考慮啊，可以考慮進入到條文㗎啦。係啊，主席。主席。
但係，即係如果佢啲文件畀唔足我哋咧，即係即係嗰度，我覺得咧，即係唔好咁急。哦，唔緊要，即係畀畀個時間我哋睇一睇，因為大律師公會嗰個文件都都係，我覺得寫得非常之係嘅，係好好長好詳細嘅嚇。噉我可以畀大家啲時間收到之後咧，如果啊，秘書處再聯
落到大家都係認為都係仲係開多一節咧，專嚟討論嗰啲文件咧。噉我哋都可以嘅，都唔係話一定急到誒不得了。不過都都要注意時間進度，因為成個都拉後咗㗎啦。
係，唔好意思，我正話發緊夢。你正話講嘅日子係幾時啊？六月四，六月四，六月四，四點三十分至六點三十分，會係下一次嘅會議。好嘛，好噉啊，我多謝大家參加，多謝。
多謝政府。